<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Apple Hot News</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/hotnews/</link>
<description>Hot News provided by Apple.</description>
<language>en-us</language>
<copyright>Copyright 2008, Apple Inc.</copyright>
<webMaster>rss-feeds@apple.com</webMaster>
<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2008 14:50:56 PDT</pubDate>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2008 14:50:56 PDT</lastBuildDate>
<category>Apple</category>
<generator>In house</generator>
<docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss/</docs><item>
<title>Meet the Actors: Steve Carell and Anne Hathaway</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/retail/soho/?sr=hotnews?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>On June 18, just two days before the hilarious Get Smart opens in theaters, stars Steve Carell (Maxwell Smart) and Anne Hathaway (Agent 99) visit the Apple Retail Store, SoHo, to discuss the film, screen clips, and answer audience questions. Seating is limited, so come early to the 9:00 pm event.</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2008 13:05:42 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Computer Music offers “The Ultimate Guide to GarageBand”</title>
<link>http://www.computermusic.co.uk/page/computermusic?entry=cm_special_the_ultimate_guide</link>
<description>The leading magazine for digital musicians dedicates its latest print issue to one topic. GarageBand. Computer Music’s June issue (with its included DVD) includes a dozen video tutorials, offers an exclusive “Best of Jam Packs” loop collection, features interviews with Fall Out Boy and Alex Greenwald, and includes plenty of demos and GarageBand songs to hone your audio editing skills on.</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2008 15:59:04 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Macs help reveal how dinosaurs ran</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/science/profiles/manchester/?sr=hotnews?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>The duck-billed Hadrosaur dubbed Dakota grazed the area now known as the North Dakota badlands some 65 million years ago. Unearthed in 1999, Dakota yielded not only soft tissue (an exceedingly rare find) but also near-complete mummified remains. Using a Mac Pro cluster, University of Manchester scientists are now discovering how the 7000-pound looked, walked, and ran.</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2008 10:32:47 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Get the exclusive Get Smart clip</title>
<link>http://phobos.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewMovie?id=281305805&amp;s=143441</link>
<description>Be among the first to see the exclusive Get Smart clip now available — free — on iTunes. It’s introduced by stars Steve Carell and Anne Hathaway, who play CONTROL agents Maxwell Smart and Agent 99 in the film. Get Smart comes to theaters throughout the country on June 20. Enjoy.</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2008 07:59:33 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Men’s Vogue recommends the gift of Time Capsule</title>
<link>http://www.mensvogue.com/magazine/slideshows/2008/06/fathersday?slide=3#showNav</link>
<description>Rather than another tie, Chloe Kamarck (mensvogue.com) thinks the “responsible Dad” will appreciate the reassurance offered by a simple yet rock-solid backup solution. Time Capsule, Kamarck explains in the magazine’s Father’s Day Gift Guide, “works with Time Machine software (built in to all Macs with OS X Leopard) to seamlessly and effortlessly back up your computer on a regular basis.“</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2008 16:29:09 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Apple previews Mac OS X Snow Leopard at WWDC 2008</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/macosx/snowleopard/?sr=hotnews?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>Developers attending Apple’s Worldwide Developers Conference got a glimpse at Mac OS X Snow Leopard, the next major version of the world’s most advanced operating system. Scheduled to ship in about a year and optimized for multi-core processors, Snow Leopard will enhance the performance of Mac OS X, set a new standard for quality, and lay the foundation for future OS X innovation.</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2008 16:09:50 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Apple introduces the new iPhone 3G</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/iphone/?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>The new iPhone 3G combines all the revolutionary features of iPhone with 3G networking, built-in GPS, and iPhone 2.0 software that supports Microsoft Exchange ActiveSync and runs hundreds of third party applications built with the iPhone SDK. Available in 22 countries on July 11, iPhone 3G comes in two models: an 8GB model priced at $199 (US) and a 16GB model priced at $299 (US).</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2008 11:38:00 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>iPhone 3G to be available in more than 70 countries</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/pr/?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>Together with its partners — América Móvil, AT&amp;T, Bharti Airtel, Globe Telecom, Hutchison Telecom, O2, Optus, Orange, Rogers, SingTel, Softbank, Swisscom, Telecom Italia Mobile, Telefónica, TeliaSonera, T-Mobile, and Vodafone — Apple will bring the highly anticipated iPhone 3G to more than 70 countries worldwide beginning on July 11.</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2008 11:37:00 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>iPhone SDK downloads top 250,000</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/pr/library/2008/06/09iphone_sdk.html?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>Since its launch on March 6, Apple today announced, downloads of the iPhone SDK (Software Development Kit) have topped more than 250,000. The iPhone SDK provides developers with the same rich tools Apple itself uses to create its native applications for iPhone. Customer in 62 countries will be able to use the new App Store to wirelessly download applications created with the SDK directly to iPhone and iPod touch and start using them immediately.</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2008 11:35:00 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Announcing the MobileMe Internet service</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/mobileme/?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>The new MobileMe Internet service delivers push email, push contacts and push calendars to native applications on iPhone, iPod touch, Macs and PCs. A subscription-based service with 20GB of storage for $99 (US) per year for individuals and $149 (US) for a Family Pack, MobileMe provides a suite of elegant, ad-free web applications — Mail, Contacts and Calendar, a Gallery for viewing and sharing photos, and iDisk for storing and exchanging documents — that deliver a desktop-like experience through any modern browser. </description>
<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2008 11:34:00 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>UK University Lectures on iTunes</title>
<link>http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/education/7431918.stm</link>
<description>BBC News reports that University College London, the Open University, and Trinity College Dublin are putting lectures onto iTunes U, which now features content from universities in the UK, Ireland, Australia and New Zealand. “Our students will be able to revisit materials presented to them in lectures, so they can learn anywhere and anytime,” says Professor Peter Mobbs of University College London. Learn more about iTunes U by watching their new video tour.</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2008 17:43:19 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Pro Tip of the Week: Welcome to Wikipedia!</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/pro/tips/wiki.html?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>Probably you’ve heard of Wikipedia, the revolutionary online encyclopedia. Perhaps you’ve used it, too. But did you know that you can now access Wikipedia directly from Dictionary?  Or from any Mac OS X Leopard application that supports it, including TextEdit, Mail, and Pages? Read on.</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2008 10:43:19 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>“Get Smart” at the Apple Retail Store, Third Street Promenade</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/retail/thirdstreetpromenade/?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>If you’re in Santa Monica, California, on Saturday, June 7, come to the Apple Retail Store and hear director Peter Segal and Dwayne Johnson (who plays Agent 23) speak about the eagerly awaited film, “Get Smart.” The first of a series of Filmmaker Talks featuring cast members of the new comedy, other Filmmaker Talks will take place at the Apple Retail Stores in SoHo (New York) and San Francisco.</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2008 11:40:35 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Celebrate Black Music Month</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/retail/events/blackmusicmonth/?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>June is Black Music Month. Apple is celebrating by hosting an impressive lineup of hometown blues, R &amp; B, hip hop, jazz, funk, and rock artists performing live in several Apple retail store locations across the country. Check out the store locations and performance schedules, and stop by to see and hear your favorites.</description>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2008 12:15:55 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Quick Tip of the Week: Managing Browser Tabs</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/business/theater/#tutorial=managingbrowsertabs?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>Safari and Leopard make it easy to browse multiple websites in the same browser window using tabs. This quick video tip demonstrates how you can manage your desktop more efficiently by using tabs to consolidate and rearrange all your open browser windows in one.</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2008 17:38:56 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>“The best notebook screen in the world”</title>
<link>http://computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;articleId=9087318&amp;intsrc=hm_list</link>
<description>Belongs to the 17-in MacBook Pro, proclaims Ryan Faas (computerworld.com). “The brightness and color brilliance is out of this world,” he says. What’s more, the system “delivers all of the processing power, RAM options and storage capacity of an iMac — along with approximately the same screen real estate,” making it “a desktop replacement in virtually every sense of the word.”</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2008 15:57:12 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>The Tracey Fragments: She’s in Pieces</title>
<link>http://www.apple.com/finalcutstudio/action/traceyfragments/?sr=hotnews.rss</link>
<description>“There was no other choice,” says Jeremy Munce of the decision to edit “The Tracey Fragments” using Final Cut Pro. Adds director Bruce McDonald: “Whatever we thought to do with Final Cut Pro, we could do,” he says. “In a way, the film looks like it does because of its radical fluidity. We could not have achieved our vision without it.”</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2008 10:04:47 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>Sign up for a free “iWork for Business” seminar</title>
<link>http://seminars.apple.com/seminarsonline/iwork08/apple/index.html</link>
<description>How do business owners use Pages, Numbers, and Keynote? In the free online “iWork for Business” seminar, Rebecca Breitenkamp, CFO of Intezyne Technologies, tells Apple product manager Mike Greenberg how her biotechnology startup uses iWork ’08 to produce financial projections, annual reports, research updates, and many other documents. Watch it online, or download the video and watch it on your iPod.</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2008 07:53:38 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>PDN names MacBook Air “the ultimate travel companion”</title>
<link>http://www.pdngearguide.com/gearguide/content_display/reviews/e3ic8cebb424120f3a5fb66d8974c1e53fa</link>
<description>After testing it on a trip to Europe, technology editor David Schloss (pdn.com) found MacBook Air an “incredibly powerful computer in the world’s cutest package.” He “was really impressed with the glossy screen,” proclaims the keyboard “the best I’ve ever used, period,” and calls its real-world performance “naturally perfect.” He also touts its performance browsing and editing images in Aperture.</description>
<pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2008 09:40:50 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
<title>15-inch MacBook Pro is Editors’ Choice for PCMag</title>
<link>http://www.pcmag.com/article2/0,2817,2279376,00.asp</link>
<description>“Being perfect out of the box is a tall order,” points out Nicole Price Fasig (pcmag.com), but the new 15-inch MacBook Pro met her high expectations. In fact, she found it “a stellar system from the start.” Naming it “our new Editors’ Choice,” she gave it a 4.5 star rating (out of five).</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2008 15:26:12 PDT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>